Hello and welcome back to another
episode of It's Dr. Dan and today we're
going to be learning about different
types of chemical reactions. So when it
comes to chemical reactions, there are a
few major types you're going to come
across in general chemistry um when
you're learning about these. Now, the
whole idea about learning the different
types is so that way you can predict
what kind of products you're going to
come across when you are introduced with
two initial reactants. So, what we
learned about when we learned about how
to balance chemical equations. So, we're
going to go through each type and then
we're going to try to predict what it is
exactly that we will be making following
a very simple recipe. So, for these
different types, I would recommend
writing down the little recipes. That
way you can try to see what components
you have. So for the first one,
combination synthesis. With combination,
it's exactly what that name is. We're
going to be combining two different
things together. So we will have two or
more substances and they'll combine into
one single new product. So if we have
two separate things, a really simple way
to put that, A + B is equal AB, right?
We're taking A and B and we're mushing
them together to make the same exact
thing. So an example of that type of
reaction would be let's say if I had two
different species. What if I had
hydrogen gas reacting with bromine gas?
So with this we can kind of see we have
two of those individual parts. Now
they're going to be coming together.
Now, when we're predicting this, the way
that we're going to be assigning letters
is essentially for hydrogen. Hydrogen is
a single element. That's going to be an
A. Bromine is a single element. That's
going to be B and it's going to be
creating a B. Now, you don't want to
just write that it's going to be H2 Br2.
That's not an actual chemical formula.
So we have to go and write down how try
to think how many bonds can everything
make. Well, hydrogen can make a single
bond. Bromine can also make a single
bond when we're looking at this specific
interaction. The other way to try to
remember too is if you remember all the
charges, we're going to have to be swap
dropping them along. So it builds off of
everything that you've learned
previously in chemistry. So being that
it's a plus and a minus, they are
balanced. So we have a correct product
but we have to also go through the
process of balancing it. So if you can
see on the right we have or sorry on the
left hand side we have two hydrogens. We
only have one on the right on the right
hand side. We also only have one bromine
on the right hand on the right hand side
of the reaction and one or two broines
on the left side. So with that how can
we easily balance it? Well, we can add a
two coefficient out front to balance our
reaction. So, not only are we
predicting, but we're also going through
a balancing act as well. So, it's a lot
of different pieces all coming together.
The next major type is a decomposition
reaction. Decomposition is when one
substance breaks apart and forms two
separate uh products from this. So we
start with one and we break into two. So
we're decomposing or breaking down. This
is the opposite of the one we just
talked about. So if we are to be going
through something that's like
decomposition, well, we got to go
through a very similar process. We have
So let's say if I give you a starting uh
reaction of HGO, so mercury oxide, and I
ask you, all right, well, how would this
break down? Well, we would assign our
little letters, right? A would be for
mercury, B for oxygen. So that means
it's going to be breaking down into its
individual pieces. So it's going to
break down into mercury and oxygen. Now
one thing about this is we have to
remember other little skills. If you
have individual elements forming, we
have to remember our datomics as well.
So if you remember the seven datomics,
just to kind of write those down for
ourselves. So if you remember have no
fear of ice cold beer, this is going to
help you a lot for future reactions.
So being that oxygen naturally forms O2,
we have to remember to write that
subscript there. Same thing when we're
balancing charges, we're always checking
our subscripts. Now, is this a balanced
reaction? Right now you'll see that
there's two oxygens on the on the right
hand side and there's one oxygen on the
left. So how could we easily balance
that? Well, if I put a two in front of
HGO, that balances our oxygens, but now
our mercuries are imbalanced.
So now we'll balance that one. So it's
decomposition. We broke down mercury
oxide and then we made mercury and
oxygen gas as a result.
The next type is when we're looking at a
single replacement reaction. So this is
when one element in a compound is going
to be replaced by another element. So
the way that I showcased this was we
have A as an element and that's going to
be coming in and replacing
our B in this case. So when that
happens,
A is coming in. It's going to replace B
and then B is going to go away. So this
is a singular replacement. So being that
this is a single replacement, there's a
couple little trends that are easier to
remember here. Elements that are that
tend to form cat ions will replace other
cat ions. So for example for A here a
lot of times this tends to be a metal.
Metals generally will form cations ions.
They have a positive charge. So if we
have an ionic species that it's reacting
with well it's going to replace the
cation. If you have a let's say if a
instead is something that makes an
annion maybe like if it's like a gas
like chlorine or bromine gas iodine gas
these ones are going to be forming
annions. So they'll replace the other
portion of it. So let's try to let's
look at an example of that. So if I go
through this and I say we have copper
reacts with zinc chloride,
how would this reaction occur? Well,
copper is a metal, right? So that's
going to have a tendency to make a
positive charge. So we can assign our
letters, right? So this would be a plus
b c. And what that's going to be
creating is A is going to replace B
and then A and C are going to be
created. So copper is going to replace
zinc. That would be one product. And
then we're going to be creating copper
with chlorine in our final product.
Okay. So now in order to go through
balancing these, we got to look at all
how many of each species do we have.
Well, one thing you'll notice is our
actually everything is balanced in this
one. We don't have to do anything with
it. So this one's already balanced. The
only way that this might require
balancing is depending on which form of
copper you have. This one is a 2+. You
could also have a oneplus, which might
affect your balancing. But you can see
that copper
replaced
zinc in this reaction. Zinc went away
and it went into went into by itself. So
it was we replaced one single element.
The next one is double replacement. So
with double replacement, the entire idea
with this one is that we have two
compounds reacting in an aquous
solution. So whenever I say aquous that
means that we have generally an ionic
species that is in a aquatic solution.
So it has water around it. So whenever
we have water this is something where
the cations ions and the annions they're
going to be trading with one another. So
with this if I say that's going to be
trading the best way to remember this
one is think of inside outside meaning
that the things that are typically cat
ions in these. So these larger ones are
cat ions these two are going to be
trading place or we're going to be
trading places with the different parts
here. Meaning
when this is happening and we're trading
our cat ions, A and C are going to be
trading. Meaning that A and D are going
to bond together. So the outside bond
and then the inside bond together. So
we're going to be trading. So what would
be an example of that? Well, being that
this is in an aquous medium, we can say,
what if I had silver sulfate
and this is going to be reacting with
sodium chloride,
what would I be creating? So, from this
particular example,
we're going to be trading our inside and
our outside. So, we're going to be
taking our silver and that's going to be
bonding to chlorine. So, why don't we
write that over here? So, A G C L. We'll
write our charges to make sure
everything's balanced. In this case, we
see silver has a plus one charge,
chlorine has a minus1 charge. So you
have to look at your period trends
with sulfate and
sodium. They're going to be bonding
together.
And let's do that in a different color.
So sodium and sulfate
we will have those. So it's Na+
and then sulfate is a 2 minus. So
they're going to trade charges. So swap
drop meaning that it's going to be
sodium 2 with just a single sulfate.
All right. Now with balancing we have to
make sure that we are checking all of
our how many of each species you have.
So these are a little bit tougher to do.
The first thing you want to do is start
with the polyatomic. Right? So we have a
single sulfate on both sides. We see
that there's one on both. So let's start
with the sulfate on the left. the one
that's bound to silver. So, we'll now
balance the silvers. So, we're doing the
zigzag method. Start with sulfate.
That's balanced. We're now going to go
to silver. We see that there's two
silvers on the left hand side and
there's one on the right. So, we will
add a two in front of here. We'll then
go to the chlorines.
We see that. Okay. Well, now there's two
on the right. We now need two on the
left. and the sodium's balance as a
result of that as well. So we have a
balanced chemical equation. But this is
double replacement. It's all about
trading. Remember inside outside the
outside bond together, the inside bond
together when you are going through
those types of reactions.
So there's two more. So we have
combustion.
So combustion, if you think about how
does your car move, how do you heat your
home? It's all about burning fuel. So,
and that's the most common example that
you'll see in general chemistry. So, if
I want to burn a fuel source, generally
what is going to be happening is you
have what we refer to as a hydrocarbon.
So, hydrocarbon is hydrogen bound to a
carbon. It's the simplest fuel source.
Think like propane gas, gasoline,
methane. These are things that are
hydrocarbon. So whenever we are given a
hydrocarbon, let's say if I pick
methane, the end part of the reaction is
always the same no matter what. So
oxygen, every gas needs to burn with
oxygen. In order for fire to happen, we
need for it to burn with oxygen. So CH4
is going to react with O2 as a result.
Let's uh make these a little bit bigger.
So CH4
is going to be reacting with O2. Now
that's going to be creating CO2
and water. Now what we need to do is
check is everything balanced. And the
one thing that you'll notice carbons are
balanced. The hydrogens are not. So one
thing we can do is we can put a two on
the right hand side. That's balanced.
the oxygen's we have four on the right
only two on the left so we can balance
that with a two then we have a nice
balanced combustion reaction so it's all
about the burning of different fuels now
the last type of reaction so this is
going to be one that I'm going to make a
separate video on by itself but this is
something that you that you're going to
come across because it's a subtype of a
lot of single single replacement
reactions as well as sometimes for
double replacement and combustion too
but mainly single replacement. So what
this one is all about is how your
batteries work in your cell phones, your
laptops, all your electronics. It's all
about the conduct how we can conduct
electricity which is in the form of
electrons being transferred from one
place to another. So in oxidation
reduction it's how do we transfer an
electron. So I made one here with just
zinc and hydrogen. So zinc in this case
is transferring electrons to hydrogen to
help power something. So what this is
referring to is writing out all the
charges or oxidation states of these
different species. So we're always
writing out the charges which are
oxidation states. And this is something
you're checking in all reactions to see
like okay is everything balanced. And
sometimes you're going to see the
charges on different species are going
to change as a result.
So when this happens, so if I have zinc
reacting with two hydrogen plus ions,
we're going to create zinc ion and H2
gas. So you're going to see some
bubbling come off. Now, if we look at
the different pieces of the reaction,
zinc with a zero charge turns into zinc
2+. So this one lost two electrons. When
you lose electrons, that is oxidized.
Okay? So lose electrons
is oxidized.
Now the opposite is when you gain
electrons
you are reduced. So hydrogen in this
case gained two electrons so it was
reduced. Um now this is the final type
of reaction. So the main five are these
first ones that we covered but you will
commonly see oxidation reduction too
which we will cover more in the future.
I hope that this video helped you.
You'll be able to see the different
types and maybe practice a little bit of
balancing as well. But feel feel free to
tune in for future videos. We're going
to be coming up with some new ones in
the near future. Um being that we're
always producing them. I look forward to
seeing you in the future. And this has
been Dr. Dan. Please hit that like,
comment, subscribe button, keep the
channel going, and I really appreciate
all of your support out there. All
right, bye. And I'll see youall later.
[Music]